Guide to the Department of Germanic Languages and Literature Records, 1949-1986 UA.25.21.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of Germanic Languages and Literature records
1949-[ongoing]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of Germanic Languages and Literature
UA.25.21.0001
5.5 Linear Feet
The Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literature was created to offer students the opportunity to study the German language and the literature of Germany at Duke University. Most of the collection ranges in date from 1960-1985. A majority of the material was accumulated and created by Herman Salinger (Department chair, 1955-1970 and faculty member, 1955-1975); and Leland Phelps (faculty member, 1961-1985 and department chair, 1970-1983). Material includes various correspondence concerning academic appointments, administrative matters, and curriculum. Major subjects include graduate students and graduate study, various committees, study abroad programs, and publications. Files pertaining to the Harold Jantz Collection are also present.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advanced notice required for use.
Provenance
The Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1983-1994.
Historical Note
The Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literature was created to offer students the opportunity to study the German language and the literature of Germany. The Department endeavored to teach the reading, speaking, comprehension, and writing of German; to promote a grasp of the literature, literary movements, and the history of German literature including movements such as Romanticism, Symbolism, Realism and modern authors: Goethe, Kafka, and Grass; and a familiarity with the cultural history of the German people including art and music. The Department also offered a focused curriculum in linguistics, the teaching of German, and the study of comparative literatures. The Department instituted an M.A. program in 1956 and in the spring of 1963 a Ph.D. program in German was proposed. The first chair of the Department was Clement Vollmer (1936-1955), followed by Herman Salinger (1955-1970), Leland R. Phelps (1970-1974 and 1975-1978), and Frank L. Burchardt (acting chair, 1974-1975). Salinger and Phelps served simultaneously as Directors of Graduate Studies in the Department. In the early 2000s, faculty members at Duke and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill began planning a joint program to combine resources and strengthen both schools' departments, and the first class of joint program PhD students entered in 2009.
Collection Overview
Collection contains material accumulated during the chairmanships of Herman Salinger, Leland Phelps and Ann Marie Rasmussen, and range in date from 1949-2013. A majority of the material is in English; however, there are items in German interspersed throughout. A bulk of the material dates from 1960-1985, then 2000-2008. The collection is divided into four series: Herman Salinger, Leland Phelps, Department Chair and Director of Graduate Study, and Ann Marie Rasmussen. The Herman Salinger series contains material accumulated and created by Salinger during his tenure at Duke University, as department chair (1955-1970) and as a faculty member. Major subjects include graduate students, job applicants and inquiries, course materials, departmental publications, correspondence, and a file containing materials prior to Salinger's chairmanship. Among the name files are Clement Vollmer, Allan M. Cartter and Peter Ilkow, a German instructor at Duke from 1956 until his suicide in 1958. The Leland Phelps series contains material accumulated and created by Leland Phelps while serving as department chair (1970-1983) and as a faculty member. Material includes general correspondence, departmental meetings, and commitments. Among the major subjects are publications: Creative Encounters: Festschrift for Herman Salinger and Aus Unserer Zuit; foreign study and study abroad programs; the Munster Program; and material concerning the establishment of a language lab at Duke University. The Phelps series is also divided into two sub-series: Harold Jantz Collection files and Committee files. The Jantz Collection files contain material relevant to the acquisition and promotion of the collection including conferences and publications. Various committees on which Phelps served constitute the committee files sub-series. As both Phelps and Salinger served in the department simultaneously from 1961-1970, there is some overlap of materials. The third series contains material pertaining to the departmental chair, including Salinger and Phelps, and the director of graduate study, 1966-1983. The fourth series contains materials related to Ann Marie Rasmussen's time as faculty member (1988-2016) and chair of the department (2006-2008), and includes information on the development of the German Studies PhD program, the joint PhD program with UNC-Chapel Hill, funding and grant information, and other materials.
Related Material
Herman Salinger Papers, 1909-1982
Duke University Archives
Clement Vollmer Papers, 1898-1983
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
University Archives Photograph Collection, 1861-ongoing
Duke University Archives
Salinger, Herman, 1905-1983; Phelps, Leland R.; Jantz, Harold Stein, 1907-1987; Duke University. Department of Germanic Languages and Literature; Cartter, Allan Murray; Duke University. Department of Germanic Languages and Literature -- Faculty; Duke University. Computer Assisted Language Instruction (CALIS); Duke University. Library -- Harold Jantz Collection; Vollmer, Clement, 1898-1972
- Herman Salinger, 1949-1977
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains material created and accumulated by Herman Salinger during his tenure in the Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures at Duke University.
  - Cartter, Dean Allan M., 1959-1961, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Courses and Curriculum, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - Course Material, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Departmental publications, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Graduate requests, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Finger, (Homer) Ellis, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Fury, Marguarite, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Holscher, Elisabeth, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Maureen, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Sandra Darleen, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Lauf, Waltraud, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
  - McCredie, Brian D., 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - McMahon, Clare, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Snyder, Elizabeth, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Ulmer, Katherine Loretta, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Wade Marjorie, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Walker, Nancy, E., 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Williams, Ann Malloy, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Woodward, Elizabeth C., 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Ypma, Heuricus, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Humanities Council, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Job applicants, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Barlow, J.D., 1967 (Box 1)
  - Boyce, Benjamin, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Evelyn S., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Cowen, Roy C., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Day, J. Kenneth, 1963-1966 (Box 1)
  - Dornemann, William E., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Fowkes, Robert A., 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Gaertner, Georg H., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Gish, Theodor, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Goldin, Frederick R., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Hartwig, Ingrid U., 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Hofacher, Jr., Erich, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Hohendal, Peter, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Hopkins, E.H., 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Ilkow, Peter, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Jaessel, Gerolf, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Sydney M., 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, Harold W., 1963-1972 (Box 1)
  - Koester, Rudolf, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Lutz, Roehrich, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - O'Flaherty, James G., 1960 (Box 1)
  - Penn, Julia M., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Pitterman, Erwein, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Salamon, George, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Schanze, Helmut, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Schliewiensky, Dieter, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Schmidt, Gerard, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Schindler, Marvin, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Shears, Lambert, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Stapf, Paul, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Stok, Miek, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Thomas, James C., 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Van Heys, Dorothy, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Wahle, Margareta, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Walker, Frances, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Watt, Richard A.K., 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Frederick E., 1949-1970 (Box 1)
  - Law School building, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Long-Range Planning Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Medievalists, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Modern Language Association (MLA), 1967 (Box 2)
  - MLA prospects, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Pre-Herman Salinger Admnistration, 1951-1952, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Scandinavian literature, 1963-1968 (Box 2)
  - Speakers, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Speakers, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Student work study, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Summer Institute, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Teaching vacancies, 1965-1975 (Box 2)
  - Textbooks, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Textbooks, spring 1975 (Box 2)
  - University memoranda, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
- Leland Phelps, 1954-1986
  Series contains material created and accumulated by Leland Phelps during his tenure as faculty member, department chair, and director of graduate studies in the Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures at Duke University.
  - Committee files, 1977-1984
    Sub-series contains material relating to the various committees on which Leland Phelps was a member while at Duke.
    - Commencement Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - Commencement Committee, Commencement speaker, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Academic Status of Performing Artist, 1979-1984 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Academic Status of Performing Artists, Report, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Comaprative Literature, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Langauge Institute Committee, 1981-1984, undated (Box 2)
    - Langauge Institute Committee, 1981-1984, undated (Box 2)
    - Language Lab Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - PEW Foundation Committee, 1983, undated (Box 2)
    - Residential Life Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Harold Jantz Collection 1977-1982
    Sub-series contains material relating to the promotion of the Harold Jantz Collection and includes correspondence, the German American Literary and Cultural Conference, committtees, and grant institutions.
    - German American Literary and Cultural Conference, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Ad-hoc Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Conference, 1977-1979, undated (Box 2)
    - Conference, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Conference definites, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Conference negatives, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Conference proceedings volume, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Conference program, 1977-1981, undated (Box 2)
    - Conference report, 1979, undated (Box 2)
    - General, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - General, 1979-1981, undated (Box 2)
    - Project miscellaneous, 1976, undated (Box 2)
    - Propsal summaries, undated (Box 2)
    - Volkswagen and Thyssen Foundations, 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - "Aus unserer Zeit," #2, 1965, undated (Box 3)
  - "Aus unserer Zeit," #2, undated (Box 3)
  - "Aus unserer Zeit," #3, undated (Box 3)
  - "Aus unserer Zeit," #3, permissions, 1970-1972, undated (Box 3)
  - Bevan, William, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - bi-weekly payroll, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Commitments, 1968-1979 (Box 3)
  - Commitments, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Computer language lab, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Computer language lab, grant, Germany, 1980, undated (Box 3)
  - Computer language lab, grant, N.E.H., 1980, undated (Box 3)
  - German Democratic Republic (DDR), 1982 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Departmental meetings, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Foreign study opportunities, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
  - Foreign study problems, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Fulbright professor, Tubingen, Germany, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Friedel, Ernestein, 1980-1982 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1954-1961, bulk 1960 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1963-1965, bulk 1964 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1976 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, 1978 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, 1979-1980, 1984 (Box 4)
  - German American companies in North Carolina, 1974-1978 (Box 4)
  - Independent Study, funds, 1976-1978 (Box 4)
  - Ingendaay, Dr. Ernst, 1976-1978 (Box 4)
  - Junior Year in Munich meeting, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Language lab, tape list, undated (Box 4)
  - Masters of Arts in the Fine Arts (MAFA), 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Munster Program, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Munster Program, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
  - National Teacher Exam, 1982 (Box 4)
  - North Carolina's School of Science and Mathematics, 1980-1981, undated (Box 4)
  - Persian Project, 1979-1980, undated (Box 4)
  - Post-N.E.H. meeting, 1984-undated (Box 4)
  - President's letter, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Proposal for computing project, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Pye, Kenneth A., 1976-1981 (Box 4)
  - Sabbatical, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Salinger "Festschrift," 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - SAMLA talk, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Society for German American Studies newsletter, 1979-1982 (Box 4)
  - Society for German American Studies newsletter, 1980-1983, undated (Box 4)
  - Society for German American Studies newsletter, 1983, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Studia Humanitas, 1978-1983 (Box 4)
  - Taylor Cole material, 1975, 1978 (Box 4)
  - University of Kassel, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - Vanderbilt Report, 1975 (Box 4)
  - William R. Hewlett Foundation, 1978-1982, undated (Box 4)
  - Year-Round Operation (YRO) Task Force, 1980 (Box 4)
- Department Chair and Director of Graduate Studies, 1966-1983
  Series contains material accumulated by the Department Chair and the Director of Graduate Studies within the Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures.
  - General correspondence, University, 1966-1980 (Box 4)
  - German Graudate Program, 1972, undated (Box 4)
  - Graduate School, general, 1976-1981 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, miscellaneous, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
  - Grant information, 1975, udnated (Box 4)
  - Inquiries, 1975, undated (Box 4)
  - Princeton Test, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
- Ann Marie Rasmussen, 1991-2013; 4
  Scope and Contents
  Includes materials related to the development of the German Studies PhD program, the partnership between Duke and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in providing a joint PhD program, funding requests to the Max Kade Foundation, conference information, and other materials from Ann Marie Rasmussen's time as Department Chair and faculty member.
  - German Dept, 1997, 2001 (Box 5)
  - German Department governance documents, historical information, and pamphlets, 1998-2001 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence on procedures to nominate Director of the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, January 2003 (Box 5)
  - Department funding and grant information, correspondence, and retreats, 2003-2007 (Box 5)
  - GS Ph. D. 1991 Discussions (Box 5)
  - German Studies Doctoral Program, undated (Box 5)
  - Grad program docs, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Visiting Professor 2005, 2004-2005 (Box 5)
  - FBB, 2006-2007 (Box 5)
  - Beginnings and Endings of Modernity, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Beginnings and Endings of Modernity conference information, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Medieval and Early Modern German Studies, FNI, 1993-2000 (Box 5)
  - Fruhe Neuzeit Interdisziplinar (FNI) Conference, 2005 (Box 5)
  - NC German Studies Workshop and Seminar Series, 2007-2008 (Box 5)
  - Lee/Ewing 2001 (Box 5)
  - Old Kade 1996-2002 (Box 5)
  - Kade, Full Proposal, 2001 (Box 5)
  - KADE, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Kade Correspondence, 2002-2008 (Box 5)
  - Carolina-Duke program information, 2002-2008 (Box 5)
  - Carolina-Duke Joint Program: Documents, 2006-2008 (Box 5)
  - Carolina-Duke Joint Program: Minutes, 2007-2009 (Box 5)
  - Carolina-Duke Joint Program: Other Working Group, 2008 (Box 5)
  - Carolina-Duke Joint Program: Faculty Working Group, 2008 (Box 5)
  - UNC-CH/Duke Collaboration, 2006-2007 (Box 5)
  - Carolina-Duke program information, 2012-2013 (Box 5)
  - XREV 1993-2002 (Box 5)
  - External Review (2001-2002) (Box 5)
  - NC Research Group on Medieval and Early Modern Women: History, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - NC Research Group on Medieval and Early Modern Women, 1995-1997 (Box 5)